Collection of Ephemera Relating to the Marketing of Books, 1742-2014: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
- Publishing Ephemera Dated In the 1800s, 1800-1899; portions of 4 boxes
  - Arthur's home magazine; The children's hour; Once a month, 1870; 41448; portion of 1 box
    Broadside, elephant folio (717 x 529 mm.); text printed in red and black; some chips and tears along edges not affecting text, previous folds, dampstaining along middle fold with several small losses affecting text without loss of meaning; very good. At head of Broadside: "Periodical announcement extraordinary! Three first class magazines containing 400 illustrations and 2000 pages of the best magazine reading in the world, for only $4.00!!" Advertised at bottom of the Broadside: "Splendid premiums. Sewing machines, cabinet organs, silver ware, tool-chests, books, &c." Does not appear to be in OCLC.
    Filed under T.S. Ar.
  - American agriculturist, 1883; 44719; portion of 1 box
    New York: Orange Judd Company
    Broadside (approx. 654 mm.); illustrations; previous folds, else about fine. At head of title: "1842-1883: The Great Agric ultural Journal of the World". Also advertising the German edition, "Amerikanischer Agriculturist," "The only purely German agricultural journal in the United States". All subscribers for the year promised a "Grand (17 1/4 x 12 inch) plate copy of Dupré's great painting valued at $4500.00 entitled 'In the Meadow'". This Broadside does not appear to be in OCLC as of March, 2014.
  - American agriculturist, 1884; 44718; portion of 1 box
    Broadside (approx. 654 mm.); text printed within a border of 19 vignettes; about fine. At head of title: "1842-1884: The Great Journal Of The World For City, Village, And Country People". Also advertising the German edition, "Amerikanischer Agriculturist," "The only purely German agricultural journal in the United States". This Broadside does not appear to be in OCLC as of March, 2014.
  - A whole temperance library in a single volume. Agents have sold 20,000 copies in five months. Apply now for good territory. The Temperance Reform and its Great Reformers ... By Rev. W. H. Daniels ... Sold only by subscription, 1878; 31704; portion of 1 box
    New York: Nelson & Phillips
    Large folio Broadside, approx. 29" x 21", printed in metal and wood type, descriptive text surrounded by 12 wood-engraved portraits (among them Frances Willard, Mother Stewart,and Lyman Beecher); previous folds, one small break at one fold, ink inscription on verso showing through the portrait of Beecher; all else very good. "Agents wanted everywhere ... Agents are having fine success, as many as fifty copies sold in one day." Daniel's The Temperance Reform and its Great Reformers was published by subscription in 1878-79, and appeared under several imprints, including Hitchcock & Walden in Cincinnati, and Phillips & Hunt in New York (successors to Nelson & Phillips). This Broadside notes that the books is "one of the most spirited and successful assaults on the kingdom of darkness," and that the author is "one of the most successful historians of modern evangelism." Not in OCLC.
  - As sung by Chas. B. Ward of "Primrose & West's Minstrels" Two Little Girls in Blue Songster. Extra edition. Price 5 cents, 1894; 45229; portion of 1 box
    New York: Wehman, Henry J., song and handbook publisher
    Large Broadside approx. 35.5 x 23.5 inches on newsprint, with large, newspaper-style heading at the top and advertisements for numerous books beneath in 6 columns; liberally illustrated with many small cuts; offered are cookbooks, joke books, fortune-telling books, books on politeness and etiquette, dream interpreters, and many other popular genre books; paper toned and with several small chips and tears at the edges with small loss.
  - Brother Jonathan, 1860; 42794; portion of 1 box
    New York: B.H. Day.
    Broadside (532 x 543 mm.); large, nearly full-page engraved illustration on verso signed "Gavit & Co."; small tears from previous folds, a few affecting text with minor loss of meaning; very good over all. Heading title: "Extra Brother Jonathan." An all-encompassing prospectus from publisher B.H. Day advertising the literary magazine "Brother Jonanthan," ("The Best Family Newspaper in the United States" and "The Best and Cheapest in New York"); as well as Song and Joke Books ("Berry's Comic Songs for White Folks"; "Wood's Minstrel Songs," which are "interspersed with Nigger Jokes..."); a new and much improved edition of James Ashton's "The Book of Nature," which "contains highly important and interesting information for Married People, or those who think of marrying, on Sexual Physiology." Also provided is an extensive backlist of cheap books; and a full description of the amenities of the "Monster Steam-Ship Great Eastern," illustrated with a view of the ship in harbor as well as a plan of her interior.
    Filed under B.H. Day.
  - Saturday night, 1880; 44721; portion of 1 box
    Philadelphia: Elverson, James
    Broadside (approx. 965 mm.); text printed in red and green; about fine. Advertisement for a weekly illustrated paper, which ran from 1865 to 1901, and "surpasses all other publications in Pleasing Stories, Artistic Pictures, Charming Variety, and Typographical Beauty". Provides subscription and club rates.
  - Mason, Augustus Lynch.: The romance and tragedy of pioneer life, 1883; 44722; portion of 1 box
    Author: Mason, Augustus Lynch.
    Cincinnati: Jones Brothers & Co.
    Broadside (approx. 914 mm.); text printed within border of 12 vignettes; about fine. Prospectus for "A popular account of the heroes and adventurers who, by their Valor and War-Craft, beat back the Savages from the Borders of Civilization and gave the American Forests to the Plow and the Sickle". With a call for Agents.
- Publishing Ephemera Dated In the 1900s, 1900-1999; 11 boxes (10 partial)
  - Bauer, Ferdinand: The Australian flower paintings of Ferdinand Bauer. Introduced by Wilfred Blunt; botanical text by Dr. William T. Stearn., 1976; 36308; 1 item
    Author: Bauer, Ferdinand
    London: The Basilisk Press
    Bifolium, folio; prospectus includes information on publication specifications, payment, delivery, and the print run (500 copies for sale). Mission statement reads "This new volume, containing a fine sleection of full-size colour facsimiles of drawings made by Ferdinand after he set off with Matthew Flinders on the first circumnavigation of Australia in 1801, will...be of considerable importance". Also includes the year's other Basilisk Editions, THe Kelmscott Chaucer and The red books of Humphrey Repton.
  - Bauer, Ferdinand: The Australian flower paintings of Ferdinand Bauer. Introduced by Wilfred Blunt; botanical text by Dr. William T. Stearn., 1976; 36307; 1 item
    Bifolium, folio; prospectus includes information on publication specifications, payment, delivery, and the print run (500 copies for sale). Mission statement reads "This new volume, containing a fine sleection of full-size colour facsimiles of drawings made by Ferdinand after he set off with Matthew Flinders on the first circumnavigation of Australia in 1801, will...be of considerable importance". Color plate proof loosely inserted. Also includes the year's other Basilisk Editions, THe Kelmscott Chaucer and The red books of Humphrey Repton.
  - Bauer, Ferdinand: The Australian flower paintings of...Introduced by Wilfred Blunt; botanical text by Dr. William T. Stearn., 1976; 36306; 1 item
  - Bauer, Ferdinand: The Australian flower paintings of...Introduced by Wilfred Blunt; botanical text by Dr. William T. Stearn., 1976; 36305; 1 item
  - Boswell, James: Prospectus for the Private Papers of James Boswell, 1928; 374; 1 item
    Author: Boswell, James
    Mount Vernon: Rudge, William Edwin.
    Folio, 14pp., with subscription sheet and facsimile of Boswell's holograph text. Format and typography in the hands of Bruce Rogers. Fine in orig. stiff red paper wrappers.
  - Gay, Walter: Memoirs of Walter Gay, 1930; 37812; 1 item
    Author: Gay, Walter
    New York: Japan Paper Company
    Single folded sheet, 8vo; prospectus for a privately printed memoir used as an example of the Papier de Rives available from the Paper Company. With a history of wove paper printed to front.
  - 1929-1942...Catalogue number fifty-five, 37967; 1 item
    New York: Limited Editions Club
    8vo, unpaginated; list of titles from the Club available at Philip C. Duschnes.Titles include Confucius's "The Analetics" (item no. 42) and Edgar Allan Poe's Tales (no. 124).
  - [Catalogue], 1970; 39394; 1 item
    Barre, Massachusetts: Imprint Society.
    8vo, unpaginated; printed in red and black; original white printed wrappers, fine. Order form and typed letter on Society letterhead laid in. With envelope in which the catalogue was mailed.
  - Strong, Katherine: ["Seasons greetings" card], 1961; 37025; 1 item
    Author: Strong, Katherine
    Chapel Hill, NC: Reflections from Chapel Hill
    One card, 12mo; decorated with image of bird "designed and hand colored by Katherine Strong"'; card also thanks the recipients "for your kind assistance". Includes envelope in which the card came, addressed to Mr. and Mrs. Laurence McGilvery of the Nexus Bookshop, La Jolla, California.
  - [Bible, linear parallel self-pronouncing edition], 1900; 37597; 1 item
    Philadelphia: A.J. Holman & Co.
    Bifolium, 4to; illustrated prospectus for "a combination of the Authorized and Revised Versions"; specimen page. Text in red and black.
  - The Dutch influence in old New York, 1924; 37811; 1 item
    Single folded sheet, 8vo; illustrated keepsake from the Paper Company, printed as an example of the available stock. Etching on front cover, blue decorative boarders. Some toning.
  - THE LIMITED EDITIONS CLUB, Incorporated. Your favorite books, the Classics of the world's literature, illustrated by the foremost artists and made into volumes of beauty... [prospectus]., 1929; 12734; 1 item
    8vo, printed at the Merrymount Press, pp. 23-[28]; ornamented title-p. printed in red and black; a fine copy in orig. red cloth-backed marbled paper-covered boards, paper label on upper cover. Accompanied by TLS dated September 10, 1929 from George Macy, LEC Director, to Wulling soliciting his subscription, accompanied by a subscription enrollment form. See Smith, p. 252.
  - Ritchie, Ward: Frederic Goudy, Joseph Foster, and the press at Scripps College, 1978; 39454; 1 item
    Author: Ritchie, Ward
    San Francisco: Book Club of America.
    Bifolium, 12mo; printed in green and black; fine. Provides specimen page. Order form laid in.
    Missing as of 2017/1/17.
  - Bradley quality books, 1926; 39256; portion of 1 box
    Springfield, Mass.
    Bifolium, 12mo; color illustrations; fine. List of 8 recent children's books from the Company.
  - Memorial volume ... The Life and Times of Queen Victoria..., 1901; 45147; portion of 1 box
    Philadelphia: World Bible House ?
    Folio Broadside (approx. 12" high), illustrated; previous folds, else fine. The Memorial Volume of the Life and Times of Queen Victoria was offered by several distributors, from Chicago, Harrisburg, Philadelphia and New York. The provenance of this suggests World Bible House, Philadelphia. "Agents wanted everywhere. Act promptly. Send 10c. for outfit."
  - Recent titles...Summer 1979, 39678; 1 item
    St. Paul: Ally Press.
    Bifolium, 8vo; black and white illustration; previous fold, else fine. Short catalogue of new and available titles from the Press, as well as ordering information on back. With TLs on Press letterhead addressed to Emerson G. Wulling and original envelope.
  - Kellogg, Spencer Jr.: The oak by the waters of Rowan. A meditative essay...with a forewrd by Evelyn M. Watson, 1927; 36887; portion of 1 box
    Author: Kellogg, Spencer Jr.
    Village of Eden, New York: The Aries Press
    Bifolium, 8vo; prospectus for the press's second book, "printed on dampened, hand-made paper and...set in fourteen point Goudy 'Antique' and an imported Spanish letter. The Foreward is sixteen point Glado-Italic. The decorations, and one illustration, are by Wanda Gág, a young Bohemian artist"; edition limited to 295 copies. Excerpts from the piece and the foreward included.
  - Blake, William: The tiger, 1931; 37001; portion of 1 box
    Author: Blake, William
    Philadelphia: Carl J.H. Anderson
    Broadside, folio (311 mm.); prospectus for this addition to the Linweave Limited Editions. Illustration by Theodore Ross and printed by Carl J. H. Anderson for the Franklin Printing Co.
  - Boorde, Andrew: The wisdom of Andrew Boorde, doctor of physic, 1936; 37017; portion of 1 box
    Author: Boorde, Andrew
    Leicester: Edgar Backus
    Single folded sheet, pages uncut, 8vo; prospectus of an abridged edition of Boorde's "The Dyetary of Helth," originally published in the 16th century and published here at the Garswood Press, directed by Falconer Scott, in an edition limited to 550 copies. Includes specimen frontispiece, illustrated by A.E. Christopherson, and specimen page.
  - Best, George: The three voyages of Martin Frobisher, 1936; 36892; portion of 1 box
    Author: Best, George
    London: The Argonaut Press
    Bifolium, 4to; prospectus for this reprint of the original 1578 edition, "issued in two volumes and printed at The Cambridge University Press on Japon Vellum, Crown 4to size, and bound in quarter real goat vellum with buckram sides, bearing a polar medallion in full colours specially engraved for the Argonaut Press by W. Monk, R.E. The edition is limited to 475 numbered sets." Also makes mention of a work in preparation, "A relation of a journey begun An. Dom. 1610..." by George Sandys; printed with the list of previous publications on the back page. Text in green and black.
  - Ballard, James F.: A catalogue of the medieval and Renaissance manuscripts and incunabula in the Boston Medical Library, 1942; 36812; portion of 1 box
    Author: Ballard, James F.
    Boston: James F. Ballard
    Bifolium, 4to; prospectus for this privately printed catalogue; sample page and sample illustration provided. Previous fold.
  - Initials from French incunabula. With 1011 reproductions and an introduction by Hellmutt Lehmann-Haupt, 1948; 36854; portion of 1 box
    New York: Aldus Book Company
    Bifolium, 8vo; illustrated prospectus for a work limited to an edition of 950 copies; only one reproduction of a French incunabula initial on back page; integral order form addressed to the press. Previous folds.
  - Montaigne: Essays of Montaigne: Selected, edited and newly done into English by Francis Carmody, 1948; 36868; portion of 1 box
    Author: Montaigne
    Alma, California: L-D Allen Press
    Bifolium, 8vo; illustrated prospectus for this edition of selection from Montaigne's masterwork, limited to 200 copies; illustrated by Mallette Dean. Order form loosely inserted. Text in red, purple, and black, border illustration in green.
  - Brown, Helen Evans: Some oyster recipes...decorations by Harry Diamond, 1951; 36852; portion of 1 box
    Author: Brown, Helen Evans
    Pasadena, California: Ampersand Press
    Bifolium, 12mo; illustrated prospectus for the second in a series of recipe books from the press, "designed by Grant Dahlstrom and printed at his Castle Press"; integral order form on back addressed to the distributor Philip S. Brown of Pasadena, Calif. Previous fold.
  - Howes, Wright: A bibliography of United States history, 1952; 36357; portion of 1 box
    Author: Howes, Wright
    New York: Antiquarian Booksellers Association of America Inc.
    8vo, pp. 5; prospectus for Howes' bibliography, publication No. 3 of the ABAA, including "Aim and scope" ("books printed anywhere, in any language, within the last two and a half centuries (1700 to 1950)"; "Americana versus U.S.-iana"; and "Method".
  - Varro, Margit: Designs to music, 1952; 36353; portion of 1 box
    Author: Varro, Margit
    Chicago: Apprentice House.
    Bifolium, 8vo; prospectus for Varro's work on music and visual design. Also includes list of other upcoming publications, including Wood-engraved illustrations by the Swiss designer Imre Reiner; A treatise on the technique of making decorative papers; Everyman's almanac; and Wildflowers of northern Illinois. Also gives the publisher's mission statement: "Apprentice House has been founded as a cooperative non-profit effort in publishing. The books to be published will consist of small editions about cultural and educational activities in the arts and related subjects." Varro's work to be limited to 2000 copies. Previous folds.
  - Chaucer, Geoffrey: The booke of the Duchesse, 1954; 36883; portion of 1 box
    Author: Chaucer, Geoffrey
    Lexington, Kentucky: The Anvil Press
    Single folded sheet, 16mo; prospectus for this edition of Chaucer's elegy on the death of Blanche, wife of John of Gautn and the second publication from the Press; "The text follows that of the Fairfax ms. 16, Bodleian Library"; edition limited to 225; list of the three titles available from the press (the Chaucer, Pico della Mirandola's "Oration on the Dignity of Man," and "The Four Gospels") printed on back page.
  - Dupont, Pierre: La statuaire préangkorienne, 1955; 39545; portion of 1 box
    Author: Dupont, Pierre
    Ascona, Suisse: Artibus Asiae.
    Bifolium, large 4to; black and white photographic illustrations; fine. Text printed in French and English. Prospectus for a work that "concerns itself with the earliest Khmer sculpture". Provides 4 specimen plates; integral order form.
  - The four gospels, 1955; 36884; portion of 1 box
    Single folded sheet, 16mo; illustrated prospectus for this edition of William Tyndale's translation from the New Testament, 1526, the Press's third publication; each Gospel to be given its own volume, each to be distributed as they are completed; specimen page (20) and order form loosely inserted.
  - Collins, Wilkie and Charles Dickens: The Wreck of the Golden Mary, 1956; portion of 1 box
    Author: Collins, Wilkie and Charles Dickens
    L-D Allen Press
  - Poe, Edgar Allan: The murders in the Rue Morgue, 1958; 36867; portion of 1 box
    Author: Poe, Edgar Allan
    Antibes, France: Allen Press
    Bifolium, 8vo; prospectus for this edition of one of Poe's most famous stories, limited to 150 copies; distributed by the Chiswick Bookshop, New York, NY. Text in red and black.
  - Ho-Shang-Kung: Ho-Shang-Kung's commentary on Lao-Tse. Translated and annotated by Eduard Erkes, 1958; 39543; portion of 1 box
    Author: Ho-Shang-Kung
    Ascona, Switzerland: Artibus Asiae.
    Broadside, folio (305 mm.); fine. Prospectus of the second printing of Erkes's translation; specimen page printed on verso.
  - Abbe, Elfriede: The revelation of St. John the Divine, 1958; 36824; portion of 1 box
    Author: Abbe, Elfriede
    Ithaca, New York: Elfriede Abbe
    Bifolium, 8vo; illustrated prospectus for an edition limited to 135 copies, numbered and signed by the artist, "printed in eighteen point Goudy Italian Old Style tyoe on Taireishi paper"; illustrations, design, hand-setting, and hand-printing all done by Elfriede Abbe. Integral order form on back page; pre-addressed envelope and a sample of the paper loosely inserted. Previous folds.
  - Soper, Alexander Coburn: Literary evidence for early Buddhist art in China, 1959; 39544; portion of 1 box
    Author: Soper, Alexander Coburn
    Broadside, folio (305 mm.); fine. "The literary evidence collected and translated in this book, primarily from Six Dynasties or early T'ang texts, is designed to make possible a much more accurate estimate of the achievements of the period." Table of contents and integral order form printed on verso.
  - Mondsee--Wiener Lieder--handschrift aus Codex vindobonensis 2856, 1966; 37934; portion of 1 box
    Graz, Austria: Akademische Druck-u. Verlagsanstalt
    Bifolium, folio; color facsimile, text in red and black; minor foxing. Prospectus in German.
  - Codex epistolaris carolinus. Band III. Die wichtigste quelle für die geschichte der beziehungen zwischen den päpsten und den fränkischen herrschern im 8. jahrhundert, 1966; 37930; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, folio; facsimile; previous fold. Prospectus for a title from the series Codices Selecti; German and French.
  - Antiphonary of St. Peter. Codex vindobonensis Ser. n. 2700, 1966; 37906; portion of 1 box
    Broadside, folio (401 mm.); colour photographic illustration on verso; "This facsimile-edition belongs to group 'A' ('illuminated manuscripts') of the series Codices Selecti; text in German and English; some soiling, previous fold.
  - Die kaiserchronik des stiftes vorau. Codex 276--I. Teil, 1968; 37932; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, folio; facsimile, text in blue and black; edges and corners showing some wear. Prospectus for 4 titles in all; German.
  - Älteres gebetbuch Maximilians I. Codex vindobonensis 1907, 1968; 37933; portion of 1 box
    Single sheet folded into 6-sided pamphlet, 8vo; color illustration. Prospectus for a title from the series Codices Selecti; German.
  - Strouse, Norman: C-S the master craftsman, by Norman Strouse and John Dreyfus, 1969; 36845; portion of 1 box
    Author: Strouse, Norman
    Harper Woods, Michigan: Adagio
    Single sheet folded into six-sided pamphlet, 8vo; prospectus for this history of the Doves Press and the third publication from the press; order form loosely inserted.
  - Drogo-sakramentar (Paris, Bibliothèque nationale, Ms. lat. 9428), 1970; 37882; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, folio (340 mm.); rubber stamp on front; "Einladun zur subskription/Offre de souscription" for a title from the series Codices Selecti; text in German and French. List of previous titles from the series printed on the back.
  - Bischoff, Bernhard: Sammelhandschrift diez b sant. 66. Staatsbibliothek Preußischer Kulturbesitz, 1970; 37935; portion of 1 box
    Author: Bischoff, Bernhard
    Bifolium, folio; black and white facsimile; rubber stamp on front. Prospectus for a title from the series Codices Selecti; German and English. List of titles from the series printed on back.
  - Neumüller, W. [and] K. Holter: Codex millenarius. Stift kremsmünster Cim. 1, 1970; 37931; portion of 1 box
    Author: Neumüller, W. [and] K. Holter
    Bifolium, folio; color illustration pasted to brown paper laid in; rubber stamp to front cover. Prospectus for a title from the series Codices Selecti; text in German and English. List of previous titles from the series printed on back.
  - Kaiser Friedrich II: De arte venandi cum avibus (Codex Vaticanus, Ms. Pal. Lat. 1071). Über die kunst mit vögeln zu jagen. The art of falconry, 1970; 37883; portion of 1 box
    Author: Kaiser Friedrich II
    Bifolium, folio; large stain to bottom right-hand corner. prospectus for a title in the series Codices Selecti as well as the 31st volume in the series "Codices e vaticanis selecti". Text in German and English. A list of previous titles from the Codices Selecti printed on the back.
  - Fall 1970, 39389; portion of 1 box
    Barre, Massachusetts: Barre.
    8vo, pp. 40; illustrations; original black pictorial wrappers, printed in white and red; mostly fine. Catalogue of titles from Barre Publishers and the Imprint Society. These include Thea Wheelwright's "Along the Maine Coast"; Edmund T. Delaney's "The Connecticut Shore"; and Shipton and Mooney's "National INdex of American Imprints Through 1800".
  - Codices selecti, serie C: handschriften fremder kulturen, 1971; 37865; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, folio; prospectus for Group C of the series Codices Selecti, with emphasis on Manuscripts from Foreign Cultures; titles from the list include the Codex Vindobonensis Mexicanus, Codex Tro-Cortesianus, Codex Vaticanus B and A, and Codex Dresdensis. Printed in German and English. Rubber stamp at top of front page.